Hello.
Hello there, John.
Hey, how are you?
I'm doing very well. How about yourself?
I'm doing good. Did you enjoy the game?
You know, I I did not watch the game.
Actually, I heard a lot about the game.
I I was on a a chat thread where that's
all that they talked about was the game.
OK.
And I I tend to just watch the highlights
after the game as the as opposed to the
game itself. So I have yet to do that.
Mm-hmm. Uh.
Yeah, well, I appreciate you.
You all let me audit a bit this morning.
Yeah.
This this will be very informative,
I'm sure.
Yeah, I'm I'm sure you'll enjoy it,
so I'm glad you're here.
Asleep.
Well, so good morning, everyone.
How are we doing this morning?
Pardon.
Yeah, morning, morning.
Oh, morning.
Good morning.
Hello. Hello.
All right,
so this is the AI assisted software
development course from code training.
And I I'll be the instructor for this
course.
It's a five-day course and we'll be
covering, you know,
some introductory topics today and then
we'll do some brownfield work tomorrow
and the next day and then we'll finish up
with some some Greenfield architecture.
I'm John Miller.
I'm a Principal Software Engineer at Code.
I've played roles over my career as a
developer, architect, DevOps engineer,
platform engineer,
test architect and release manager.
I've been working with AI as a
practitioner for quite a while now.
And I started over a year ago.
I started A blog about, you know,
using AI effectively as a software
developer.
And I've done a couple of things that I
want to show you during the course of
this that I've done on the side that you
might find interesting as well.
One is this AI practitioner resources.
You can contact me at the e-mail address
on this page if you have any questions
during the course or afterwards and my
LinkedIn.
I put a link there to my LinkedIn page so
where I post notifications of of our blog
post or.
Other co-presents presentations that
that'll be doing over the course of the
this year. So with that.
We talked just a bit about code.
So this code,
this slide is about a year old. Code is,
you know, 31 years old,
has been around for quite a while as a
software development firm.
The there's four different aspects of
code, the consulting arm,
the staffing arm, the.
The code magazine and the code training.
This is obviously part of the code
training wing of code,
but we also do quite a bit of consulting.
We have a very sizable staffing operation
and we're one of the few print magazines
left that's dedicated to software
development.
Yes.
So let's go through some quick
introductions while we're here.
So if you wouldn't mind what how we'll
we'll do this.
I've introduced myself and I'll pick
somebody out of the list and and then you
go ahead and pick the next person.
Just tell me.
Who you are, who do you work for,
what you do,
what you've done with the A I tools and
what you what you want to learn in this
course,
what you're what you're expecting to see.
Alright, so why don't I pick Otto?
Why don't you go next?
Hello, I'm Otto. I'm also with code.
I'm also a software engineer with code
for almost 20 years. And yeah,
I'm in this course because I will also be
working on teaching this course in the
future and doing a custom version of it.
For individual companies or corporations.
Great. Thank you, Otto. Can you, uh,
pass the torch to somebody else?
I will hand it over to who do we have?
Let's see, Chris.
There's only one Chris, right?
Usually there's many of us.
Hmm.
Yeah, I'm Chris Bishop.
I work with Field Boss,
a mobile HVAC and elevator software
company. I'm the senior systems engineer.
What I've done with a I tools so far with
the help of Cursor.
Is to we have a a customization pipeline
that our our customers are able to
customize parts of our product.
So when we upgrade them,
we have in the past had to manually go
through the code to see what has been
customized versus our out-of-the-box.
And so I've created a a skill for the
agent to assess the the two pieces of
code to determine what differences there
are and what's compatible with our
upgrades.
OK.
That sounds interesting.
I'm hoping to learn some ways that our
DevOps crew, which I'm a part of as well,
can streamline their processes and use AI
to.
Make things a bit more secure.
All right, thank you for that.
And can you pass the torch?
I'll pass the torch to Simeon.
Oh, hi. Yes, my name is Simeon Hearing.
I'm with Vanderbilt University Medical
Center.
I'm actually coordinating a larger course
for individuals in our organization and
just popping in here, you know,
briefly to get the lay of the land,
some of the things that we're looking to.
Vanderbilt is like many organizations use
more AI to accelerate software
development,
actually using it to integrate with our
code basis as opposed to the process of
going back and forth from a tool like
Copilot would have actually integrating
with our development environment.
And yeah, like I said,
I won't be with you guys much,
but definitely want to kind of understand
the content here and see how we could
utilize this particular course maybe more
broadly in our organization.
Thank you so much.
And I will pass it to to another fellow
here from Vanderbilt,
Christopher Rockwell.
Thanks, Simon. I'm Chris. Like Simon said,
I'm with Vanderbilt University.
I'm an application developer. I have.
I've used AI tools for coding quite a bit.
The I I've used copilot,
I've used cloud code quite a bit here
recently and so I'm I'm using it a lot
for for writing new code,
debugging old code,
building tests and so I'm just hoping to.
To become more efficient and and more
effective with that through this.
And I need.
Thank you, Crystal.
I can pass it to Tom.
Hi. Can you guys hear me OK?
Oh, yeah.
All right. Hi, I'm Tom Louie.
I work for MKS.
We we create laser drilling equipment for
flex and rigid type circuits.
I'm a principal software engineer and
I've I've used the the AI twos.
Tools more recently in discovery,
but I'd like to get some learnings from
this training and maybe how to work with
it with like large code bases and legacy
code.
So that's what I'd be interested in
learning.
um I will pass it on to Peter.
Thanks, Tom. Good morning.
My name is Peter Goostry and I also work
at MKS.
I'm the architect and lead software
engineer on the distributed data
ingestion.
Platform that we build that collects all
the data analytics from our laser
drilling systems at runtime and
aggregates it and makes it available as
dashboards and other application specific
purposes.
So I've been using AI quite a bit for the
last year,
using it to generate unit tests and.
Just in general,
I mean in my personal projects at home
and I use it to kind of orchestrate and
create repositories and salute scaffold
out solutions for me to get things going.
And what I'm really interested in
learning and I don't know if we're going
to cover it here or not, but.
It's kind of the multi agent workflow and
I'm curious about getting into.
Writer,
tester or auditor loop because I'd be
very curious to see if I could
orchestrate agents to develop.
You know, a full software system for me,
um,
and I just kind of guide and orchestrate
what it does.
So that's what I'm hoping to get out of
this.
And I'm going to go ahead and pass it to
Alex.
Good morning, Alex.
I work for MKS as well and I'm a
principal software engineer working on
laser manufacturing software,
writing software and designing,
writing and designing software for.
Laser manufacturing equipment and I've
been using Opilot maybe for half a year.
AI through Opilot as a tool and I looking
forward to learn how to use agents.
Because I just don't have time to learn
it in my spare time.
So that's my primary primary goal to find
out what is the best use of agents in my
Um.
workflow.
Uh, so I.
Used it primarily for peer reviews.
A peer review tool is another peer and as
a unit test for the generator.
Find it helpful.
I'd like to pass to.
Who was not some of this? Uh.
Then.
Can I? Is it Dan?
Yeah.
Then OK.
Yeah, Blanchard. No,
I haven't introduced myself yet.
Oh.
OK.
So my name is Dan Blanchard.
I'm a software architect. I do consulting.
I have one major client I've had for like
20 years,
but the company splits and gets bought
out, so.
I so with the same code base I'm I'm sort
of working for two different companies.
And so it's like, you know, csharp.
net Azure kind of platform.
And So what I'm wanting to get out of
this is learning how to use AI to
maintain existing code base.
I wondered if there's any.
You know,
way to train model to to really
understand the whole code base or if
that's even needed and also when I work
on a new system, just the best way.
To set all the rules and and all that to
to have it generate the code with you
know the format that that I want and with
the coding standards and and all that.
So far I've mainly just been using
Copilot in Visual Studio and Visual
Studio Code you know to do refactoring
and to help.
Making diagrams,
you know going through the code and and
and giving like the the markup for EML
sequence diagrams that I found that
really helpful recently and also just
using like cloud cloud.
Mm.
Just as a replacement for Stack Overflow.
Now when I have a question I just go to
cloud, you know,
in the like the native Windows app.
So yeah,
that's my my story and let me see if I
can find someone.
That has not spoken. See Richard Lavorgna.
I don't think I recall you speaking.
Hi, yeah, my name's Rich Livonia.
I work for the Twinth Judicial in South
Florida. I do programming, analysts,
help desk. I had a little of everything.
But yeah,
we're looking to see how we can use a I
with some of our Windows applications and
and just really how we can get.
More into AI.
We're not really doing much right now,
but we're looking to kind of get some
experience on it.
I'll go and pass it over to coworker
Steven Childs.
Yeah. Hi. Good morning. Thanks, Rich.
I'm Stephen Childs.
I'm the Chief Information Officer for the
Administrative Office of the Courts for
the 20th Judicial Circuit of Florida.
That's a mouthful. Yeah.
So obviously we're working the court
system without going into a lot of detail.
But yeah, we I I.
Was a developer by trade,
but then been director for several years
and now the CIO.
So I've been away from programming for,
well, close to a dozen years,
but still kind of want to keep my my
finger on the pulse and do oversee Rich,
who you heard from and Rigo that you'll
hear from shortly.
And so want to kind of know you know what
is possible,
what's not possible and see what the
state-of-the-art is and where it's headed
next. And so yeah,
hoping to get kind of overview.
I guess you could say that we're sort of
antiquated here in in the court system.
It sounds like most of you already have
some experience with the ad.
We're we're really dipping our toe in,
you know,
just a lot of have used it personally for
various things,
but not really for writing code in the
office.
So that's what we hope to get out of it
as a starting point and I will pass it
over to Rigo, who's also with our office.
Um.
Hi, good morning.
My name is Rigo Lawrence.
I'm a web developer over here.
I'm the researcher of the core 20 circuit,
judicial circuit and my job is maintain
mainly.
The web page and also creating new
application with applications that is
needed internally.
My goal in this course is see how we can
apply the AI to my job to make you know
more robust and.
Better and faster all the web
applications that are great.
Let me see who is missing.
Yeah.
I don't know if someone is missing.
Can you go next?
Lyle, you're you're missing. OK,
let me pass through Lyle then.
Yeah.
My name's Lyle Eubin and I work at Gene
by Gene.
Our parent companies are my DNA and
buddy's in another group,
but we do the ordering system and all the
business to business for the lab samples
come in,
we track those as we ship them out to and
also do processes.
After the lab does the results,
we take over from there and kick it
through our pipelines and send it out to
the customers.
Accuracy is very important for what we do.
So we mainly do AI and ask mode.
We haven't really done much with agent
mode. You know,
we create our own PRS and we use a GitHub
copilot to review and it's been very
helpful.
But a lot of it's still manual,
so I'm looking to get more into the agent
based set up.
I think Buddy's got it in that too,
so I'll go ahead and pass it to Buddy now.
All right. Thanks, Lyle. Like Lyle said,
we'll work for Gene by Gene.
I work on a different vertical for the
consumer product, Family Tree DNA.
I'm the software development manager.
And what we've been doing lately is
actually looking into like context as
code.
We built a repo that we're because we
have a we have like maybe 40 ish
repositories of code that span some of
them or a few years to like.
20 years so and and we have a lot of a
lot of tech debt so it it's very
brownfield with just a little bit of
Greenfield which makes it pretty
difficult to have the agents or even just
the just the regular AI copilot to kind
of.
Understand what we're trying to do.
So that that's kind of been a recent
project is trying to build a build a a
repository that has a lot of good
documentation that's curated and seems to
be helping.
A lot with making sure that the agent
understands our business,
understands our code bases and our teams.
Let's see. Oh, Al Torres,
you got your hand up.
I'll pass it over to you.
All right. Thank you, buddy. Uh,
can you hear me?
Yes.
All right. So basically I'm Al.
I work for Infosoft Consulting
Corporation here in the Philippines.
So basically we do customization ERP
working with Acumatica,
basically all in C#.
So basically what we're looking for is to
integrate our integrate AI in our
workflow and we've been looking for a
formal training in AI.
So I I have big things,
big things expecting to learn more.
So I'll pass it to Boris. Thank you.
Thanks, everybody.
I'm Boris Boris Kittman.
I'm a Senior Director for the Global
Cyber Security Engineering Group in Dell
Corporation working for the ISG
Infrastructure Solution Group.
My team and myself,
we are developing all types of cyber
security solution for Dell servers and
storages. A I personally is my favorite.
I'm working with a I code assistance
almost for two years.
copilot, Windsor, Carsor and others.
Personally I came to the course here in
order to to learn and get better
understanding of.
How to incorporate AI to create a
different different kinds of software
development artifacts from requirements
through the CICD and release cooking in
each and every step.
How to evolve AI for me?
Coding with AI is pretty obvious task
already.
There is a question mark about the
quality of that still,
but I'm more interesting in different
additional types of artifacts creation
like I said.
Requirements, design documents,
architectural diagrams from that to code
and releases. Thanks.
I'm passing to whom I think we are done.
Not sure.
I think we may be Matt.
Yeah, Matt. Yeah,
I'm passing that to Matt.
Hi everyone. I'm Matt Hoffman.
I work for Outlier Technologies.
I'm the the lead developer here.
We make a software called SansRay.
That's a compliance measurement and
monitoring software primarily for the
Health and Human services industry.
What I've done with AI primarily has just
been the GitHub copilot cursor within
Visual Studio Code.
I'm hoping that through this class I'll
be able to get some knowledge about how
to improve the efficiency and
effectiveness.
Of that tool as well as the other tools
like the the copilot agent for my team of
developers.
All right, great. Thank you.
Thank you everyone for doing that.
Appreciate it.
It's interesting to hear what you're all
been doing with a I.
Let's get into the agenda.
But before I talk about just the agenda
for this course,
I just wanted to kind of give a overview
of the the five days.
Today is going to be the morning.
We'll be focusing on just some core
concepts and we'll finish the afternoon
with quite a bit of coding in Visual
Studio code trying to build something
interesting.
And then then we get into brownfield
tomorrow. Brownfield.
There's really two aspects of brownfield
that we'll be covering.
The 1st is kind of a read only aspect.
What can you understand?
What can you use AI to do to understand
your code base?
How you can use it to, you know,
effectively measure what your technical
debt is and and then we'll spend time,
you know,
working on bringing a code base from
Brownfield into Evergreen.
And we'll talk a bit about that tomorrow
and on.
Wednesday and then Thursday and Friday
will be Greenfield,
where we'll be doing an exercise that
will take us all the way from
requirements, you know,
deeply through the implementation and as
we can get into that during the course of
those two days.
So there's quite a bit of material to
cover in the five days that we're going
to be together today.
You can see the that we'll be starting
out here.
We're just talking about AI assisted
software development.
Then we'll do a couple of sections on the
LLMS and how they work for code
generation.
Then I have a.
Then I want to talk about how to use it
effectively within a team and how to
basically to use from a team perspective.
What are the considerations that you need
to have in order for you to protect your
code base and utilize it effectively?
Then we'll actually start to dive into
copilot and just do a brief overview of
the copilot user interface and some of
the things that you can do to manage
context and we'll do some hands on work
there.
Then I have a section on mob programming,
one of the things that is interesting.
About working with AI is it's non
deterministic.
So theoretically if we all were working
on the same basic exercise,
we could all be getting slightly
different responses from AI just from the.
Context and the fact that it's
non-deterministic.
So one of the things I want to do and I
think it will be helpful in the course of
the in the course is actually just to
collaborate on on work in A I.
So we'll all take turns driving the
process and and we'll all work together
on what we're going to try to build in a
collaborative sense.
And we'll do some of that this this
afternoon or in the second part of the
course. Then we'll just do,
which is basically quite a bit of just
coding with copilot and finish it up
today.
We'll see how far we can get into
building a a a.
You know, an application. So moving on,
then let's talk about AI.
So our objective here in terms of this
course is to understand that AI code
generation and we're using Kai Copilot
and we want to be able to.
Go from the perspective that we're going
to have AI assistance and we're also we
want to learn about how to assist the AI.
So there's really less emphasis on syntax
or the, you know,
the application that we built could be
built in any technology stack or any that.
We we choose and the actual syntax we're
going to,
we're not really that concerned about
because we're going to be letting the AI
assist us in building all of that.
So there's more emphasis when you're
working with AI on some of the upfront
type activities that you would do.
And to do some architecture design,
you know,
focusing on code quality and refactoring
as opposed to, you know,
how do you do a specific task in the in
C# or some programming language with the
idea that we want to be able to move fast
with less risk.
So then let's talk about AI assisted
software development.
So I had a a thought and I put a I put a
blog post out a couple of months ago that
you know,
programming really hasn't changed,
but how we go about it has changed.
And what I did was kind of walk through,
you know,
starting at the very beginning where.
When you program the computer,
you flip switches on a panel in order to
you to enter instructions into the
computer. And the idea is that this is,
you know,
this is just the latest in the long line
of ways in which we can we can basically.
Express our our intent,
what we want the machine to do and get
the machine to respond to that.
Um.
So the so the A I assisted development is
is really kind of evolutionary.
It's not I in my mind revolutionary.
Programming has always been about
expressing human intent and.
Which what changes is the sophistication
of our tools and and expressing the
content.
So basically the asset remains we're
we're we're bridging the gap between what
we want and what we want the machines to
be able to do.
So there are a couple of things that are
I think.
Notable about the this latest change
where we're moving to AI and the the 1st
is that we're now able to express our
intent in natural language,
which is definitely something that is new,
so we don't have to be expressing our
content in some arbitrary programming
language for a particular type of tool.
We can express that that intent in a in a
much more conceptual way and we and the
the A I tools are able to better
interpret that intent and it can
translate that into into the code that
the the computer can execute.
And the other thing is that the A I has
access to a very wide range of knowledge
about programming.
So it knows in a sense more about coding
than probably any of us do because it's
it's got the information or knowledge of
all the different programming languages
that have been used.
The tools that are being used,
the frameworks and and access.
So we have all of those available.
So um.
So anyway,
that so I don't think my my point is that
it's it's really just another way for us
to essentially do the same things that
we've been doing.
All right.
So moving on then to why A I assisted
software development.
Well basically you know one of the in my
first blog post I I kind of point this
out.
It's like you know A I will give you
superpowers.
It will give you the courage to take on
code bases that few people would would
would touch use technologies that you
should know.
That maybe don't write more high quality
code than you've ever written before and
take on the nice to haves.
And I also think that this is something
interesting about what AI is enabling is
that if you take a look at what the
survey of what backlogs are looking like,
they're continually to grow.
Over time.
So everybody has more work right now than
they can actually do.
And in my experience,
we were going through backlog rooming and
determining what needs to be done.
The only things that actually ever get
implemented up until now would have been
the.
The must haves,
the things that we have to get done and
we because there's very little time to
take on the nice to haves.
And in my view this is what this will
allow what AI allows us to do because
it's able to write code faster than we
can write it,
is that it will allow us to take on more
things that we were not able to take on
before.
And so the it essentially allows us to
improve the code and and and and improve
our application so that they're they have
more capabilities that are not just the
ones that they must have,
but more more more things that make their
life easier.
If you have any questions,
just raise your hand and I'll be happy to
stop and and take a question.
Alright.
All right.
So I want to talk about a I first and
prompt first.
So this the the course is is oriented
towards these two concepts.
And so I wanted to kind of just go
briefly over what these two concepts mean
and and what they what what what we're
going to be learning as a result of that
so.
The first is the A I first development is
all about like a philosophy where A I is
embedded across the entire SDLC.
So so the idea is that from requirements
design, implementation,
testing all the way through is all done.
With the the collaboration or
collaborating with A I in that process
and when we get into Greenfield we're
going to we'll talk more about how to how
to do this A I first development in a
different aspects of it and then as a
subset of A I versus prompt first where
basically you we are always we're working
with.
The prompts and instruction files,
chat modes and they're basically first
class version control artifacts.
And so we'll be taking advantage of all
all of these AI specific guardrails and
abilities so that we can actually,
you know.
Actually use it effectively and the the
idea here is that in terms of prompt
first development is that we kind of we
lean into using a I and and writing
prompts first as opposed to.
Writing a bunch of code and you'll see in
this course we're not going to be writing
handwriting much code at all.
We're going to be using prompts and we'll
be going to try to improve our skills at
creating prompts and provide the guidance
that we need to the AI in order for it to
produce output that is acceptable.
and is compliant with what what our
expectations are.
So in terms of A I first,
this is what they're optimized for the
scope.
The scope is for A I first is the entire
SDLC where prompts are focused on that
interaction layer that the things that
how we interact with the A I directly.
A I versus the life cycle integration
where in prompt first we're looking for
trying to produce deterministic A I
behavior,
which means we're basically want it to be
able to produce code that we that that
passes our code reviews and the like.
It's optimized for velocity and
governance,
where prompt first is optimized for
prompt quality and reproducibility and.
With A I first we've got human in the
loops proven in provenance and at prompt
first we're looking for version prompts
and context control and we'll be covering
like that in this course all of these
topics and show you how they're important,
how to use them.
And in terms of how they treat artifacts
A I first,
these requirements are written with a I
collaboration and we talk.
So you're looking at you know scaffolds,
tests, tests, documentation,
provenance of course across all A I
outputs,
which means that we want to be able to
have.
Traceability and auditability in in terms
of our work with a I so that you know if
questions can comes up about how things
were done,
we can go back and look at the the the
blood crumbs that we left behind when we
were doing our work and then the
architecture assumes a I participation.
But with prompt first,
we're we're we're dealing with, you know,
instruction files, prompt files,
agents and prompt behavioural contracts,
reusable prompt modules and chat modes
and the like.
And then basically this the relationship
between the two is that prompt first is
really about mechanics,
where a I first is a more of a philosophy
of architecture and life cycle
integration.
All right.
Any questions on that material before we
go on to LLM's?
All right.
So just in a general introduction, sure.
I do have a quick question.
Sorry I did have a quick question.
So so it looks like I AI first
development is like kind of setting up
the rules you know that that's in the
code base and prompt first is like more
working on a specific thing.
Is that accurate?
What I would say is that you know A I
first is kind of all about the the SDLC
that basically going from requirements
all the way through a deployment into
production, right.
And it's really about leveraging A I
through that entire process in order for.
For you to make the best,
take the best advantage of the tools,
right?
Where prop first is all about getting the
artifacts and governing and and guiding
the artifacts that you're creating.
So you're you're dealing more about,
you know,
generating a particular kind of artifact
and making sure that the particular
artifact is.
What you expect it to be. So in in AI,
in AI first,
we're we're going to be using agents and
custom custom agents in order for us to
be able to give and we'll be giving those
agents skills and and expectations about
how we want them to.
Actually function at a high level.
And then we have, you know,
things like prompts and prompt files and
instruction files that actually are part
of the prompt first realm,
which drills down into how you actually
produce.
Uh, specific artifacts.
Does that help explain it?
Yeah.
Cool.
All right.
So let's then talk about large language
models.
So basically we're going to go through a
a conceptual overview,
talk about some capabilities and then
talk about using a I as a tool.
So LLMS are trained on massive data sets
of code in natural language. So in fact,
and I think they've at this point,
they're pretty close to consuming all of
what we've been publishing in on the
Internet and consumes books and all kinds
of additional information.
So it's a huge body of knowledge.
Then they use what's called a transformer
architecture to understand the patterns
in that that data that it's collecting
because it doesn't understand the data
until it starts to actually process it.
It uses a token based processing where
the code is broken into.
Tokens and we'll talk quite a bit about,
you know,
how to manage those tokens because
there's a finite number of them that that
we can leverage.
It uses attention mechanisms and to focus
the model on relevant parts of that
context.
So and so we're taking this this
information.
The data that we're that the the model is
ingesting,
we're transforming it to using it to
understand the patterns in that data and
tokenize it so that so that we can
actually then start to query into that
that that into that knowledge base.
Using attention models to focus on the
things that are relevant because
associates with that huge body of
knowledge,
we need to be able to pick out the things
that are important and then it generates
A probabilistic next token prediction
based on the training patterns.
And so this is important is that there is
no true understanding pattern match.
It's just pattern matching at a matching
scale.
It's really statistical prediction of
from 1 token to the next token about what
should the what is the best choice from
that and.
When you we put all this together in
terms of this this processing,
you know it it produces the the amazing
results that we're seeing from AI when we
actually give it a prompt and get a
response back.
So it's really you know this this
technology is really broken through and
and really provided.
Interesting capabilities.
So we can do things like code completion,
code generation, refactoring,
code optimization,
bug detection and and remediation,
granular documentation,
test cases of code,
explanation and commenting and multi
language support and translation between.
Languages.
All of these things are now very easy to
do to leveraging AI,
and I heard you in your introductions
mentioned most of these as things that
you've already been experimenting with.
Some limitations and I have a caveat here
is that these limitations are changing
over time.
Things are getting as the tools and the
and the the models are improving and how
they're implemented improve these these
knowledge,
these these limitations are start to
lessen up a bit.
So for example,
no real-time knowledge and updates.
Some models actually will incorporate,
you know,
least recent data from the Internet
because they beyond their cutoff dates so
that they can actually add some more
pertinent temporal.
Questions that are more relevant to
things that have happened after those cut
off dates.
You can generate statistically correct
but logically flawed code.
I I've got some examples of this I'll
show you as we go through the course.
I'm sure if you've worked with it at all,
you've seen.
Where it's correct code,
but the code isn't actually logically
capable of executing. Chris,
do you have a question?
Yeah,
it was about the first item there with
the opening of a lot of these models to
like web search.
I'm wondering how relevant that first
item is.
Well, I'm saying that's why my person,
my caveat. Yeah,
this was something that is becoming
increasingly less of a of a limitation
because the models are are becoming more
current or have you know capability.
Hmm.
They essentially are adding on
capabilities that allow them to if
they're not getting a decent answer or
can't or they.
From their own internal knowledge base to
do actually searches of the of what's in
the lab currently.
Thanks.
But yeah, that's a good,
that's a good point. All right.
So then the hallucinations, again,
we've all heard about that is basically
and and I'll talk about this when we talk
about, you know,
context management and how to manage the
context window.
And so the and the context windows has
limitations which is a finite amount of
memory.
And again going to a lot of caveat about
changing every as models evolve they they
they tend to increase their context
windows which basic which basically gives
us more elbow room for us to be able to
put in information.
And get the the responses back.
Does it that it does not understand
business logic or domain specific
requirements,
although this is really hard to prove out
in a in a sense that it's you know it it
it at least makes it appear as if it
understands that business logic.
But doesn't actually have any innate
understanding.
And you know,
can only because because that only really
doesn't understand that business logic,
therefore it can't really, you know,
make reasoning efforts to.
To extend that business logic beyond you
know what you what it understands about
that particular requirement and you can
potentially introduce security
vulnerabilities if you're not careful
about it.
And there's also a a risk of of bias from
the training data.
We we've heard about this in, you know,
with images and other things like that,
but there's also some chance of bias from
the the training data and when we get
into a section where we talk about.
Comparing different implementations using
different models, you can actually.
I was actually able to demonstrate it.
You can get biases for a model will
essentially like its own code that it
that it would that it would generate over
the code of a of a different model even
if.
The other model implementation might be
more sophisticated in some some ways.
So the idea is that there are biases in
the in the models that we have to kind of
mitigate for and and the context of and
takes be conscious of and take steps to
try to.
Address.
All right,
so let's talk about the LNM in in the
architecture that used for code
generation. So I have a diagram here.
I'll zoom into this.
We did.
There we go.
So this is basically talks about this
process of where we have a developer
input with natural language and code
context and so the idea is that we we
give it a prompt and we provide some
context for understanding that prompt.
And then what the the LLM does is it will
then tokenize that text.
It will take that text and convert it
into tokens and and then those tokens get
embedded into or transformed into into
into vectors.
And then they get,
then it goes into the transformer layer
where it basically goes that applies that
attention and feed forward logic to try
to essentially incorporate the token, the,
the, the,
the prompts that we give it in the
context along with all the training data.
And code repositories and documentation
that that is in the repo and then there's
a fine tuning or code code specific
training that goes into the model where
the the model is tweaked for particular
outputs.
Once all of this transformation occurs,
the context goes into the context window,
which is that limited memory buffer for
understanding what the requests are.
It goes to that the pattern recognition
and code patterns and syntax,
where it starts to actually understand a
bit more about the.
The prompt and what in the context it
does this then probability distribution
and next token prediction where we
actually determine what that next token
should be and it goes through that
process repeatedly until it actually
finalizes.
A solution using a decoding strategy,
greedy beam search sampling.
This actually them determines what that
final output is.
Then we go to the cogeneration port,
which actually took.
Takes those tokens and and that and turns
them into text output.
It does send some post processing and
validation.
More more effort is being put into this
phase of the model lately models lately
to try to basically reduce the the the
variability and to increase the accuracy.
Of the models and then finally those we
would do some developer review.
And if it's acceptable,
we incorporate that into our code base or
we go back and refine our prompt and then
and have the AI try again.
Any questions on any of that?
All right, so in.
So just this is just a snapshot that I
took a couple of weeks ago of what of the
models that are currently available or
available at that time.
And you can see that in in Cobot there's
quite a number of different models
available.
These models have specific capabilities
we could which we can see in terms of
whether like support tools and vision and
other kinds of media output.
It also here displays that the input
context size limits are.
As well as the output context sizes and
and so this effectively you're saying for
if we look at pod side for five,
it has 128K of an input context window
and then a 64K output context and if you
exceed any of those.
Those windows,
then you start to introduce variability
and unpredictability into the model or
into the output.
So any of the multipliers these will vary.
Well, the models, of course,
will vary over time. Models come and go.
And and particularly in terms of specific
versions,
I think there was the ChatGPT came up
with a a new version as well as well as.
Claude and the multipliers vary with your
subscription level.
So depending on what subscription you
have with copilot,
you'll get a a multiplier for what are
called premium requests.
And you get a certain window or number of
those premium requests during the for for
in a month. And then if you use them up,
then you're basically having to wait till
the next month before you can submit any
more premium requests.
And I'll get when we get into the the UI,
I'll show you a bit about how that's
managed.
And how you can kind of keep track of
where you stand within these,
these with these context windows. Yes,
Chris, another question.
Sorry John,
I was just wondering because I have
worked in industries where it's been
important if there are data residency
options when choosing these models or
data security and governance essentially.
Yeah. So that goes,
I think that gets into, you know,
where the model is and where the data
that you send it gets used, right.
So we'll talk about some of the controls
that you have in co-piloted in in a
little bit later in this in the morning.
But yeah,
from a data residence perspective,
you probably control.
You can control what copilot does with
that information.
So you if you provide it,
you can specify whether or not that
information actually gets used by.
By the LLM or or not,
we'll get into some of that idea,
but you could you essentially could say
don't use my information as a part of the
model and that way you can kind of
restrict this,
keep all that information essentially
local to your machine.
You also have the ability to run some of
these models locally.
Thank you.
And that's an emerging trend where you
would, you know,
get a big box and you would basically
host these models and on a local machine
and or at least some of these models on a
local machine and then you'll be sure
that none of that information actually
goes into the cloud.
Thanks.
Sure. All right.
So just looking at models,
here's some information that you can kind
of that you can use to help you compare
these models or understand what they're
good at. So I'll,
I'll just talk briefly about some public
leaderboards for this,
some core benchmarks,
some surveys and research that's that.
People are doing on against them and then
some evaluation frameworks.
So so these are some public leaderboards
that do where they do model to model
comparisons.
So this LLM stats coding leaderboard
aggregates some 20 odd coding benchmarks.
So is the top performers across all these
different.
Benchmarks.
So this will give you and these things
change as the models try to leapfrog each
other in terms of cogeneration.
So you can it's a good idea to kind of
keep your finger on the pulse of these to
see which ones are are are.
Are are really good at particular types
of activities.
There's also a Tech Radar Coding LLM
guide that does a comparison of strength
of different models for different
different kinds of activities and Zen
Coders model comparison that breaks down
their accuracy reasoning and.
Their context window.
So these are good just overviews of what
the how the models compare.
You can look at some core benchmarks.
These benchmarks are basically.
Measure the the the performance of the
model, some functional correctness,
the contamination free holistic benchmark
for his live code,
some and and and the PP is some simple
algorithmic tasks across different
languages and models.
There's a a real world GitHub issue
resolution benchmark and then there's a a
depth quality eval benchmark. Again,
just more information on how to compare
the models and what the models are are
specialized in so.
Academic surveys that some comprehensive
overviews of tech techniques and
benchmarks.
Some explainers that about the strength
and weaknesses of each benchmark and how
to interpret the results and then some
specialized benchmarks.
For a domain specific coding evaluations.
And then getting into some evaluation
frameworks, these two you could actually,
you know,
host yourself and actually run some
frameworks.
If you have specific requirements that
you really want to to measure different
models against,
you can use these frameworks to build
those tests and to run those evaluations.
All right.
Any questions on those comparing those
models? And so with the selecting model,
you just really want to kind of align
them with your workflow.
You want to be able to combine your hands
on work that you're for the the tasks
that you're familiar with with also the
the leaderboards you want to.
You won't.
You may want to build a repeatable
internal benchmark suite because the
models change over time,
and so if you have a a specific thing
that you're already looking to benchmark,
it would be a good idea to be able to
codify that so that you can execute it
every time the models are updated.
And you want to attract contamination
free benchmarks for reliability.
All right.
So let's talk about teams and things that
we have to be concerned about when we're
doing development as a team.
So we want to empower developers with AIY
protecting your code base.
So the benefits to an organization,
I think is pretty,
it's becoming pretty clear, you know,
faster prototype.
Typing few of overplay tasks that need to
be executed,
so it's accelerating our development.
Our documentation is improving.
We can even, you know,
have it automatically keep our
documentation in in line with what the
actual implementations are we have.
You know enhanced testing and the ability
to really really improve our our test
suites and our our our confidence in our
testing and then our our the team
productivity which in terms of we're
talking about reducing our cognitive load
and supporting onboarding.
You know, one of the,
I think one of the real,
real nice benefit that comes out of using
AI is it's our ability to give it to
somebody that doesn't understand our code
base and have them just use AI to help
teach themselves on how the code is
actually built.
All right.
Some risks that we need to consider as a
team would be IP leakage.
I think this was something that Chris was
just kind of referring to.
So we want to make sure that that.
We have control over our information that
we're providing to that A I.
So for example, code,
code pilot may suggest code that is
similar to public repositories and
there's a and we want to be able to
manage that.
There's a risk of inadvertently using
copyrighted or licensed code,
so there's a.
There are public code filters and we want
to and we also tend to want to review our
suggestions,
but the we can actually say that.
We don't want to,
we want to exclude from consideration in
terms of code generation,
anything that's publicly coded,
coded and that's available.
Code quality and accuracy. Yeah,
we all know it could contain,
it could contain bugs,
inefficiencies or security flaws and we.
We always want to validate and test
before we do a deployment and I think as
we'll see as we get into the course
deeper that our our ability to to build
out test suites that can can catch these
kinds of issues is really a key aspect of
of of using a I effectively.
We can treat copilot as a drafting tool,
maybe not as a source of of truth.
So the idea would be that we we can
essentially use a prompt first approach,
use AI to generate something,
but then go back and update it or tweak
it to.
To to be exactly what we want.
And then there's a obviously a risk of
reduced understanding or critical
thinking related to the the to over
reliance on on a I generating a lot of
code but not understanding it.
We want to encourage code reviews and
pair programming to maintain, you know,
our intellectual ownership of of the work
that we're doing.
So then we also have a compliance risk,
regulatory compliance I'm working with.
With a group right now who have FDA
requirements that they have to meet and
so we're working on developing the
internal standards to to guide their use
of A I in order for them to be compliant
with the the FDA regulations.
And you can do the same thing with HIPAA,
PCIDSS.
So organizations,
you must enforce these coding policies
and audits that make you want want to be
able to be able to defend the the work
that you're doing and how you're doing it
as being compliant with the the standards
that you're subject to.
I actually have a a Co presents webinar
to present some of this work that I've
been doing with with this particular
client.
I think it's gonna come up in April and
I'll go over some of the techniques that
I've been I've been using to understand
what the level of compliance.
What the gaps are,
how to address the gaps, etcetera.
So data privacy and security is sensitive
data.
I mean it should be never be typed into
prompts.
Use copilot in secure environments with
clear usage guidelines and and then
there's also a license ambiguity code.
copilot suggested made Zumbo code under
restrictive licenses.
Legal teams should define acceptable,
acceptable use policies and and monitor
compliance there.
Good.
And then through terms of IP and data
protection.
So one thing to note is the the code that
you have in your repository that you're
exposing to to to copilot is not used to
retrain the model.
Um.
You so with both business and and
enterprise version.
So you if you're using it within an
organization you you you should seriously
consider you know a business or
enterprise licenses so that you can get
access to some of these.
Higher level controls in order for you to.
Keep keep control of your IP.
Suggestions are generated locally.
No code is shared unless feedback is
submitted.
There's no leakage between your your
users, your code,
your private code is not exposed to other
users,
and then admins can disable suggestions
matching public code.
For added safety and I you can do this in
your in the pro versions as well and I
can show you that in GitHub.
And we talked about the, you know,
codes similar to public report.
There are filter blocking to match public
code,
but you should also take a look at the
co-pilot's terms of service and privacy
statements to make sure you fully
understand what they're doing.
So your deployment options you use.
So there's the Pro and Pro Plus as as
well as the free version of Copilot
individual.
There's limited IP protection in those
products.
Copilot for Business adds more admin
controls and policy.
Enforcement which is stronger and then
strongest is an enterprise license with
org wide policy and audit tools that you
can that you can leverage.
So safe use,
use those public code filters,
establish a a a a review process and
stick to it,
and then make sure the whole team is
educated on what the proper use is and
for the code that gets produced.
And then there's a couple of resources
here for additional documentation on this,
the copilot documentation that the using
for business overview and a security and
privacy fact are all useful sources for
understanding how to use it effectively.
OK.
So now let's get into.
Just a hands on with copilot.
Can I ask a question about that?
So, yeah, sure.
Yeah. So you know,
in in in the organization that I'm
consulting with,
I don't think we're really using the
business one.
I think everybody's kind of using their
own. You know, there's a,
there's a variety of consultants,
full-time employees.
So if they're using their own,
like me personally,
I'm using like my own account,
my own 365 GitHub account.
That means what I'm sharing like with a I
would go to like they could use that to
train it and that could possibly leak out.
Is that correct?
Yeah, that's that's the concern, right.
So that's why the the,
the business license.
And and the enterprise licenses are are
preferable in an organization if you if
that's a concern that you have.
So if you were to add for example of
files from your repo to the to your
contacts and then you would ask a prompt
for the A I to understand something about
that file, it's going to upload that file.
And depending upon how how you configured
copilot,
it will then determine what it was,
what what it's allowed to do with that.
So so me as a personal user like can I
tell it to like not share it or is that
only like possible in the business or
enterprise?
Yeah, well, yeah, I, you know,
my to my understanding,
the business in the enterprise versions
are the ones that have the greatest
control over that.
Uh.
But I'll take a look at the I think I
would suggest take a look at the the
privacy and document to to determine
exactly what they'll do with that and in
the terms of use.
OK. All right. Thanks.
Alright.
All right,
so does anybody not have GitHub Copilot
installed at the moment?
Does anybody not have a GitHub account?
All right, so good.
We're gonna assume that that's OK and
we'll move forward from there.
I just want to go through some things
here, explore some UI components.
If we've installed it and have our
account,
we can basically talk about the chat
window, new chats, quick chats, settings.
And the model dropdown.
So let's just kind of bring up.
Visual Studio code honey.
Increase the does that everybody see that
OK?
Yeah, that looks good.
All right,
so this is our main interface into the
chat window.
We can open up a chat here and we can
open up a quick chat.
The difference between the two is that
this would be like the main chat
interface where we can enter.
Our prompts and then we can do what's
called a quick chat and that'll bring up
a prompt here where we can actually enter
a prompt.
The benefit of this is that this they're
essentially like two different chat
sessions going at the same time,
so they don't interfere with each other's
here,
which you've built to your contacts here.
Go up here and ask a quick question and
and get a different answer or solve a
different problem. So that's useful.
We can see here in the chat window that
there's a number of options down here.
We'll talk about adding a context in a
second.
Go there now.
Basically the idea here is that we have
this idea. We have a a content window.
We talked about how that gets tokenized.
Well,
here's a a way that we can provide
information to to the A I that it can use
as a part of that context that helps
focus it.
When you're actually achieving a prompt.
So when you're running a prompt,
it will then use, for example,
the files and folders that you're you're
currently working with,
and that allows you to basically specify
a particular file.
Or or the like or we have um.
And you can see here it adds that context
to to our chat window and tells us that
this is going to be used as a part of our
prompt. You can go to go to GitHub issues,
you can have it look at a poll request.
You can actually do this more often where.
You wanted to take a look at an image
from a clipboard.
Maybe there's something on a screen in a
that you that you want to have as a part
of your context.
You can just take a screenshot of it or a
clipping of it and paste it into the chat
window and it will then do an OCR and
understand and actually understand what
the context of that clipboard is.
You can use our called instruction files.
We'll get into that in tomorrow's course.
MCP resources.
These are tools that are published from
third parties or from Microsoft that
provide additional.
Functionality and I have a number of
these tools installed.
Some of my favorites,
the ones I use most often are are tools
related to git,
so you can actually have it, you know,
understand you know what the what a.
The current state of a git repo and help
you navigate git,
particularly if git is not your strong
suit. But I I've had it to, you know,
do things like, you know,
take take a look at two different
branches and tell me what the difference
between those two branches are.
I've had to look for branches that don't
have to have commits that have.
Have not been merged to main. Well,
things like that are really easy to
accomplish using AI.
This will actually go out and take a
screenshot,
take a look at your source control.
You can look at the problems that have
been identified and you can have it then
try to.
To address those problems,
you can look at your symbols from your
files and then add additional tools from
third party sources.
So these are all ways that we can add to
our context and that context really helps
us to find what specific things that we
want the AI to.
Focus on in a way,
these all kind of act as ways to take
that huge body of knowledge that the AI
has and shrinking it down to just the
things that are important to accomplish
this particular task.
And then that helps keep our context
window under control and help us focus
the.
On the kinds of answers that we're
looking for over here.
This is new in the latest version of
Visual Studio and Copilot for Visual
Studio extension where we can we can run.
Tasks locally.
We can run them as background tasks or we
can run them in the code in in code and
this is a.
We can also delegate it to Claude,
the cloud coding agent.
And so these are new capabilities that we
can take advantage of and this is
something I can we'll talk about in a bit.
But the idea is that we can delegate to a
background or a sub agent now and have it
perform those tasks in a different
session.
And it gives us the ability to actually
have a I actually, you know,
multiple things concurrently and in the
case of of going into the cloud,
if we were to talk about this one,
what it will do.
Is will it'll actually create a a a new
branch.
It will execute the the command or
whatever the prompt is on that new branch
and then create a PR to merge that branch
into back-to-back to main.
Here is our our agent modes.
So we have our,
so we have the different chat modes.
One is the agent mode, the ask mode,
edit mode and plan mode.
We'll talk about those in a little bit.
And then we have here these are two new.
Agents that are are added by default that
and you can and then when we talk about
configuring custom agents,
we'll talk about how we can add
additional agents.
So for example here is one that's a focus
on data and analysis.
We can create other agents that are
focused on different particular roles
within our software development lifecycle.
Things like a a a a product manager for
for defining requirements,
a a security expert that understands.
How to perform security tasks,
things like that,
and focus the the A I on on a specific a
particular set of skills and a particular
approach to solving a problem. And again,
it allows us to focus the A I on specific.
The specific things as opposed to just
general knowledge.
Here's where we would choose the
individual models.
This is kind of where I got that.
A list of all the models and here you can
see the.
The.
What the what the the um?
What the premium is on on these signal.
So these models here would be free to for
me to execute these.
These models have a different premium
token of premium execution values.
So the idea here is that.
This one is 1/3 of a a a a third of a
premium request.
So you could do 3 premium requests for in
this model for the price of one in cloud
4.
And you can see here that this cloud Opus
4.6 is 9 times.
So every request will essentially reduce
your number of available premium requests.
You can see those premium requests down
here.
You can see that so far this month I've
used and I'm using a a Pro Plus plan and
I've used now so far this month 20% of my.
Of premium requests.
So when when I when I use them up then
then I'm allowed no more premium requests
that month unless I decide I want to pay
for those additional premium requests and
you can see that it will be reset at the
end of the month.
Oh, at 4:00 PM. That's interesting.
All right. So, yes, Buddy,
you have a question.
Yeah,
for I I I pretty much see the same thing
and it might just be the way I have it
set up with my we have a enterprise
Right.
organization,
but when you were selecting what type of
what is it a session you wanted?
You you had that Claude one.
Is that like a a a different extension or
Mhm.
is that just like something I'd have to
configure to have that show up?
This this I did not do anything to have
this show up other than just up.
Oh, OK.
I upgraded Visual Studio code and I
updated and I updated the extension for
Yeah.
copilot in the extension tab.
OK, yeah,
I had updated mine right before like this
morning just to make sure because they've
been moving so fast lately and I and and
and like I saw some of these newer
updates,
Right.
but I still don't see the Claude one.
But maybe,
maybe it's the Copilot extension that's
not updated yet.
It could be that or it it could be.
I have a Claude license.
Oh, OK. Maybe it's that. Yeah, I don't.
I don't have one.
It could be that, it could be that,
you know that this just showed up,
you know,
a couple of days ago with an update and I
haven't had a chance to actually
determine what.
And for the I I guess one more question I
have like the for the premium ones the
What? What is that?
Sure.
like when you run out I have it set to
auto auto pay request is enabled which is
something that we we're trying to
experiment with.
So that one would just mean it just pay
as you go, right?
Yeah, it would turn into pay, right?
And I I'm, I don't recall.
Like once you reach a limit.
What the pricing is on that,
you know how many,
you know how many premium requests you
get for a dollar or not, but.
Yeah,
we've been monitoring it and then it
seems pretty reasonable,
but we'll see how it goes the more people
are using it in our organization.
All right. I I mean I I pretty,
I think you get a quite a quite a a
Thanks.
budget for the enterprise license.
So I think you would need to have a a
Yeah.
pretty large team of developers to where
you would start to reach those limits.
All right, right. Sure. Other questions.
Great, cool. All right.
Thanks.
So let's move on to the talk about the
the MCP tools.
So these are the tools that you have that
I have and you can see some of them I
have disabled and some of them I.
Enabled and the reason you kind of need
to look at this and and the copilot will
or Visual Studio code will notify you if
you exceed this.
But you're you're limited to 128 and I
have 86 selected so and you tend to want
to keep these.
Try not to select too many of them
because it does impact your your contacts
window. It tells you for example.
With your copilot.
What is it here? Is it workspace? No,
I think that was.
In a different part and I'll have to try
to show you when we get into prompting,
but yeah, so.
There's these are different tools.
There's some built-in tools that do
things like search for files and you can
invoke these directly by saying I want to
use this particular tool. For example,
I can say if I have a question about
Visual Studio code, I can say.
Vience code.
Or you can or you can say something like
at GitHub.
And there's two different tools here from
GitHub,
which is one the general questions about
GitHub or and or about specific PRS.
And then once you've selected one of
these, there are.
Additional options that you can gain
about each one of these that they publish
individual commands that you can access.
So.
So anyway, so take a look at that.
Take a look at these tools. You know,
all of them are fairly useful in
different aspects,
but what we want to try to do is minimize
them because if we exceed them,
exceed the number of tools,
then we'll start to get warnings that
we've got too many.
You know these tools activated.
All right, some questions on that.
So this is allows us to dictate or start
a voice chat. Yeah, one of my.
One of the things I've aspire to is teach
the entire course using all just voice
chat instead of having to type in prompts.
And then we have the the send option
which will basically submits a prompt for
processing.
Up here there's start a new chat,
a new chat editor window or a new codec.
So this is coming from.
I think that comes from Open AI.
Which I also have a license to.
Here those are some settings that we can
access to in for defining custom agents,
profiles, etcetera.
Oh,
so moving chat windows into new windows.
There's a debug view as well,
which is useful when you're trying to
understand exactly how a prompt is being
processed.
We can go into a full maximum size bar
size. We can close the window itself.
All right,
so any other questions on just this basic
UI?
The only other thing I can probably I
have a file here.
Um.
There's the slides.
I have them in this repo. Um.
I'll talk about this later,
but this is a this is a repo that you
guys can clone and what we'll do is we'll
put all of our all the work they're gonna
do to the course into this particular
repo.
So you'll have a a a record of it and the
slides are already in that repo.
Uh.
Can we use a PR for a Azure DevOps or is
this only work for GitHub?
I mean maybe there's sort of plugin or
something I guess.
You would have to look for a tool to
support that.
I believe there is a tool to have it.
There's a quick, you know,
if you just do a search for this repo in
GitHub,
you'll find it and you'll be able to
clone it from there or just look at it.
So Chris posted in the chat that Azure
Devox no longer supports the PR extension.
So, so.
But you know,
maybe there's a third party solution to
that. A lot of, there's a lot, a lot of,
a lot of tools out there. So let's see,
let's go back to the slides then and see
where we're at.
So I showed you the premium token uses
bar, talked about trading it.
So create a new chat and experiment with
that interface.
One thing I didn't talk about is the
sessions, so.
So this shows you that the all the
sessions that you're running every time
you start a new chat.
You're effectively starting a new session.
So I was interested in here and seeing um.
You could do something like for GitHub
what what open the arms.
And there's there's no there's no PR
associated with it,
so it shouldn't find anything.
But you can see here as we're executing,
it converts that to to search to doing a
search and it tells us there are no open
PRS if we were to create a file.
Um.
And then say go ahead and.
Right.
Uh, PR or use.
So it sees there's no active pro request.
It's it's doing some work with git and
this is a good point to to talk about
this because you you see here that it's
asking me to allow it to run this git
commit commands.
And So what I could do is I bring this
down and I can say I I only want to allow
commits in this session or I want to
allow them for this entire workspace that
I'm working on right now. Well,
I can always allow git commit,
but I've chosen not to do that.
Um.
Because I don't want to have commits
going into the repository without me at
least reviewing them or approving them
before they go in.
You can say allow this exact command line
or you can set and then again that can be
for the session for that workspace or all
always.
You can allow all commands in this
session,
which is not something I would recommend,
and if you choose to configure them,
it will bring up a file for auto
improving and it shows then.
All of the different way basically it's
describing the rules for for auto
approving things, for allowing things.
So this will say OK Oh yeah,
allow all commands starting with make
there so I can make all the folders that
I want.
I can run NPM run build right all these
different commands and you can also use
reg expressions to do this.
And if you go and look at it and at it in
Jason you can see all of your auto
improve settings here.
What this allows you to do is essentially.
Fine tune the interaction between you and
and and copilot so that you're not
constantly approving commands.
But you know you know with the what what
do they say with great power comes
responsibility.
You need to make sure you're.
That you're you're not approving things
that that are destructive and that's what
I tend to say. OK, don't delete anything,
but you can you can you can view it or
show it.
So we could then say go ahead and allow
that commit.
So it's going to commit that resource to
the repo and it wants to do a a push to
the origin with a new feature branch.
You can see here it's created a new
branch for that PR request.
So still push those changes.
We have no more pending changes.
Oh.
Um.
And so it wants us to create the pull
request in in the branch and we can say
you know use.
No.
You know it's CLI to the.
Oh well,
so I have something in this workspace
that's a little bit different than what I
I typically use, but I wonder.
Mhm.
I'll I'll look at that at lunch and let
you know what the dish is.
But typically I I can do this and it'll
automatically create a PR,
give you a link to the PR where you can
go and review it and and move on from
there. All right, so that's.
So we've talked to,
worked with the extension.
We've done a quick chat,
we found the chat history and did the
sessions.
So let's just talk just a bit about
prompt engineering and prompt specificity.
So.
Here we could have a prompt that says add
error handling to my code,
very generic asking what type of errors,
what language, et cetera.
So I could ask you questions about that,
particularly if you don't have a
particular piece of code open in and in a
context.
Um.
It's it's also very generic,
which means that you don't have very much
understanding in terms of what you're
what you're what you're actually asking
it to try to do.
So you what you're really doing is you're
asking A I to infer from from its
knowledge what what it actually expects
you to.
What your actual intent is,
and this is where you can run into issues
where it's actually not understanding
your intent correctly.
That happens occasionally and inferences
is a is a like a you know,
it's both a good and a bad thing, right?
So in some cases it's not good because it
can infer the wrong things.
In other cases,
it can infer things that you hadn't
considered and actually can add value
quite to more generic requests,
and I'll talk about that a little bit
later.
But here's a more specific version of
that same prompt where we're adding error
handling to a JavaScript function that
calls.
An external API.
So this is much more specific and it says
you want to handle network timeouts for
for us and parsing failures and then you
want to return user-friendly error
messages.
And here is a even more specific where
we're actually referring to a specific
file.
And we want to add components of error
handling to deal with network timeouts,
you know, errors.
And here is also referring to a error
types file that has error messages that
are already in an existing format than
that you want the AI to emulate.
So the idea here is the more specific
pictures,
the the the more context that you're
giving it,
the more precise of the result that
you're going to see from the from the AI.
All right,
so let's talk about context management.
So we're gonna we we talked a little bit
about this, how to add add symbols,
how to understand the context window
limitations and talk about effective
prompts.
So here are these add instructions.
So if we do this we can see them.
Here's a whole list of these.
These are are some of our tools as well
as some built in things that we can take
advantage of.
So you can see here for example.
The Azure tool has added all of these
additional commands that we can add to
the Azure tool and have an understand for
mermaid diagrams.
We have a series of options here.
Ms. sequel for building tasks.
We have some built in.
Here's the workspace, explain workspace,
fix workspace, new. These are all.
Workspace is now the replacement term.
I have mentioned maybe in a couple places
for app code base,
but it's now it's it's now it's a
workspace command that's changed recently
and so this basically allows us to.
Perform additional operations or
different or different commands that the
the A I understands.
Basically keeping us from having to type
in a longer prompts,
but if we can just mention a particular
command on a particular.
Aspect of that that we want to execute
and it will do do that for us.
All right,
so that workspace for searching across
the whole code base or include the whole
code base in your context a specific file.
These are interesting in the sense that
you can do that terminal.
Here which will bring a look at the
contents of the terminal window.
And then here's the VS code for asking VS
code, for example specific questions.
There's also a hashtag.
Or.
Option and this brings this will bring up
the the any files that we have in our
workspace or any files that are open in
our workspace.
We can access and add them directly into
our context and.
And here we can have specific commands
that we want to execute strictly by
entering the the hashtag in the
appropriate command.
All right,
so we talked about the big prompts.
I had here a context window experiment,
but I attempted to do this over the
weekend and I couldn't get it to
reproduce. So the.
The uh.
So there's a a context, excuse me,
in terms of the context window.
The idea was here to to basically start a
long conversation and and watch how that
affected the context window,
trying to get it to over overflow the
context window and demonstrate the.
Where it had forgotten particular
instructions.
This was easier to demonstrate,
but there's been a lot of improvements
into the tooling and I was able to
demonstrate that I'm getting an error
from a copilot indicating that it
exceeded the context window instead of
actually.
Producing invalid results,
it gave me an error and in many cases it
refused to actually execute commands
because they would actually exceed the
context window and it couldn't and it
knew it couldn't give me accurate results
as a as a a function of that.
So let's add some things. Switch back to.
Um.
To the switch to this branch.
And I have this context window here and
this is this is the chat that I was using.
You can kind of you can review that if
you want.
Where I was trying when I was attempting
to actually exceed the window and wasn't
able to demonstrate it.
But as a part of that I created AI
created a huge file with a lot of context
in it so you can.
Reference this large file in your context
and then say um.
Well, I don't think you know number of.
Ones.
But um.
Something like this.
So it's still working on it and.
We can see here that there's a local
agent in progress.
As it's trying to actually.
Um.
Scan this large file.
What was the?
All right,
so one other thing I mentioned while I'm
here is there's this checkpoints in the
chat window.
This will actually restore the workspace
in the chat to that point,
which means that if I've generated any
content from my prompt and I don't like
it.
And I've proceeded to execute other
prompts.
I can actually go all the way back to
here and restore that checkpoint,
restore back to that previous point,
and then that will.
That will then basically revert those
changes.
Now that will go all the way up to the
point that you actually have, you know,
accepted those changes or or committed
those modifications.
All right,
so it's still thinking about this.
All right, so let's, uh, move on.
We can come back and look at this in a
minute.
So we looked at all the contact types.
Um.
So talk about under when when to start
first chance sessions.
This is a this is a good point because
you notice here that in this session I
have mixed two different.
Activities.
What is the work that we're doing on
pushing in that and creating that phone
request?
And I've mixed that in with this exercise
here about the context window.
This is this is probably something that
we would try to avoid.
It's always a good idea.
And you're moving on to a different task
to create a new chat. What that will do,
it's a couple of things. One,
it will clear the copilot from the the
context that you currently have
established.
So it will discard anything in its
context related to this.
Pull request that we're trying to create
and um.
That way we get a fresh context window
when we're actually starting a new chat.
So that and it also allows us to start
make sure that we have sessions and you
can see here that that we have a a list
of all this.
I have a list of all the sessions that I
was using.
To help build build out this repository
yesterday and today and you can see here
this is our our work.
Related to these report requests also
concludes this this additional work.
So we would want to create a new session
and and a new chat in order for us to be
able to isolate that work and be able to
go back to that whatever was done in that
work.
And so for example,
I can I'll go back to this particular
point and I can see the work that I was
doing in that particular chat chat
session.
So you have a a a history then of of the
work that you've been doing.
And if you're using sessions correctly,
each one of them will be focused on a
particular conversation that you want to
that you had with the AI.
All right,
so let's talk about just chat management
and workflow.
So we talk about organizing our chat
sessions effectively and and looking at
our chat history and we want to start to
develop our official workflow patterns.
I always go back.
Here.
Yeah, so they they move that.
So let's go back to our existing chat
session.
Yes.
All right,
so chat organization we we wanna we
reviewed our chat history.
We talked about chat that should have
been in separate sessions. We talked,
you know,
showing you how to create new chat
sessions whenever we need to.
And.
We want to start and focus our chats on
one specific conversation or feature,
add the relevant context and complete the
task without that the context overflowing.
And then for a quick chat,
we would use the quick chat for main chat
for a primary task and then quick chat
for side questions. I also use, you know,
external chat windows from other,
you know, from other interfaces as well.
You know,
just to separate the the the the tasks
out again if I'm just doing a a
completely unrelated type of a search.
And then you would can return to your
main chat without without my losing
context.
The chat history review we we showed
basically how to find and reference a
previous solutions,
how to learn from a those past prompts
allows us to go back and look at the
previous prompts and.
Examine how they worked and reuse them
and identify patterns and effective
conversations with the idea that,
you know,
if we find that we're actually getting a
lot of prompts or very similar problems,
we can actually talk about turning those
into a prompt,
prompt files and actually making them.
Part of our code base and allow us to
read them regularly.
All right,
so we've talked about chat history quite
a bit and finding and referencing
previous solutions.
And that we want to be able to move.
To use a multiple chat windows
efficiently in order for us to isolate
our our our different works work streams
that we're focusing on.
So just remember context is a limited
resource.
We want to not start new chat and
changing our changing our focus area.
Keep those conversations targeted and.
If you if you start noticing that a
copilot,
a copilot is starting to forget earlier
context, it's time for a new session,
which means that it doesn't seem to
recall. You know,
essentially the chat window works is you
add chat to to the when you add chat to
the window, the oldest chat gets removed.
Well,
the all this context gets removed so that
and so that then causes it to no longer
understand those instructions that you
would have in that earlier context.
Alright then.
All right, the find out. OK,
so this is one thing I was looking to try
to generate was this little icon here and
this is also new.
It gives you an insight into the your
context window.
Basically it's telling me here that I've
used to.
45K of my 109 remaining available tokens
from its context window after they take
out the system instructions,
the tool definitions.
You can see here all those 86 tools I
created.
Uses used up a 14,
almost 15% of my contacts window.
And then I can see that by for my context
that it's tool results is 8% of that the
files itself is majority is 9% and the
messages that's are are 7%.
So when you're working in a chat you can
use this as a peek to peek into.
Your context utilization.
And the other thing I should mention is
that here I I can say go ahead and I can
just cancel this this task.
And that will then stop the stop the
execution of that particular chat.
So that's that was what I wanted to get
to and actually executing this large file.
Another reason I wanted to show this.
What? What was that?
Well, I guess that's.
Oh, that's what it was, I would say.
Another interesting prompt would be.
So you can you can basically say uh.
You can basically tell it to uh um.
To to do some some rough calculations
based on the number of tokens.
So if you're working in a particular file,
you can you can ask it to, you know,
give you a sense of what the what the
token consumption would be for that file
and you can also.
Until Copilot or to to actually optimize
a particular artifact to minimize the the
the token,
the number of tokens it consumes and and
to target,
for example execution by an A I agent as
opposed to a something that would be
interpreted by a.
Human developer or or the like and that
will produce substantially different
outcomes.
It will it will be much more turfs in
terms of the the output file that it
creates as well as.
Minimizing the number of examples and
other other content that would increase
the number of tokens consumed without
actually.
Improving the the actual content of the
file.
So it's it'll have the same intent but
with a with a lot less verbiage and a lot
less tokens consumed.
All right, so let me try this.
A different model.
So this is the output that was created by
the diagnostics.
Tells you what custom agents were loaded.
There they are instructions.
The prop files that were.
Use the skills that it loaded.
So this gives you an insight into the
actual what it what it used to build the
context that you can actually you can
look at.
No, I think I'll down some minutes.
And I'll stop that shot.
All right. No, uh, Dan.
Yeah, I just had a question.
Does if if you if you're you know the the
stats with the context,
if it's getting too full,
does it do like auto?
I don't know if compression's the right
word,
but like Claude now has a feature where
it does that like if it starts getting
too full, it'll just.
It'll it'll refine, you know,
it'll kind of compress the information so
you can keep going.
Does this do that as well or does does it
depend on which model we're using?
I haven't seen that.
I think that's a feature of cloud code.
Not cloud code, but like cloud. Like,
yeah, well, just just in, you know,
Model.
using using cloud like in the browser.
I I have seen whenever I'm using copilot
that it every once in a while I'll say
summarizing conversation.
I wonder if that's kind of the a similar
feature that Claude's trying to do.
I yeah,
I I've seen that as well and I I think
you're right that is it's basically we'll
talk about that.
Um.
Well, yeah,
we'll we'll talk about something like
that. Um.
A little bit later in the course.
Uh.
So, uh, sorry.
Yeah,
which was basically when we get into a a
section we we talk about how to how to
manage that context window.
We can that's some of the what's one of
the techniques that we can use ourselves
is it's to basically take a large
conversation or a large file that we want
to include in our context and then have
it.
Summarize that file.
Um.
And then use the summary as a part of the
context instead of the actual file itself,
and that can reduce the number of tokens.
Okay, thanks.
OK.
And now the the different modes.
This is pretty straightforward.
The idea at least is there are different
modes that have a different impact in
terms of how copilot operates and so let
me.
Drop that, get out of here and.
We have here the the the different modes
that we that are available.
When when the copilot was first
introduced, it only had an ask mode.
You could just ask it questions,
it could you could write code and it had
some capability of inserting that code
into files.
But it couldn't create files on its own
or uh or add.
Or modify existing code.
All you could do is ask the questions and
get responses back and you can still do
that and what this would you can have it
you know you know create.
Uh, get.
I think I've got something going on.
There's no open sessions.
So can't having trouble getting it to run
those prompts.
Under me restart.
This code.
OK.
All right, that cleared that up.
So I'm asking it to create a file in ask
mode.
It'll put the file directly in the chat.
And.
There's an icon here that says apply this
in the current editor,
so we have an editor open that we would
add it to that.
You can insert it on a particular cursor
or you can just copy it and paste it
someplace else.
Or you can put it into the terminal or
here we can say I want to create a new
file for that.
So not to ask about any questions on that.
Chris, you have a question?
Yeah,
I just noticed when I ran that it goes
through every MCP server that's indicated
there in the toolkit.
And I noticed you mentioned before that
the fewer you have,
the better the context.
I'm just wondering,
it looks like there's an MCP server for
every extension that you have that has an
MCP server available.
If we're just doing work in C#,
for example,
is there a quick way to get rid of all of
the non-related MCP servers in that
There are typically.
dialogue?
Install the VN extension so you can just
uninstall those extensions.
Right.
So that's the that would be, I feel, well,
if you wanted to permanently get rid of
them, right?
Yeah,
if I if I'm just working in a workspace
that's say Java based maybe and I only
want to use some Java based MCPI don't
need to use the SQL ones,
I don't need to use right?
Is there a quick way that I can just
deactivate the ones that aren't
applicable?
To this particular workspace.
Yeah, well,
you obviously have the tool menu itself,
right, where we could.
Or we could add or or or deselect them.
So you could do that here,
but I know I don't know of a way.
Mhm.
Off the top of my head where it where you
can persist that from a project by
project basis.
Right. Not yet. Anyway, it's fast moving.
Yeah, I haven't seen it. I could be. Yeah,
you know, you never know, you know, but I,
you know,
now maybe something that I've missed.
So I I could, I could look for it.
OK. Thanks. Yeah.
Cool.
Yeah, Phillip is gonna chime in on that.
Hey guys. Yeah, hey John.
If you click on that cog wheel up on top
Hi.
of the copilot chart,
you should get a tool set menu item.
Oh, nice.
Click on that tool set.
And you can create tool sets where you
can you know well create the tool set.
You have to.
You can also do this inside of a what
they.
Call custom agent now it was called chat.
So if you click on the on that little.
That money.
Now on the on the bottom where you have
explored, understand your code right now.
Yeah, on the very left. No,
that's this one. OK,
it's it's just a little bit different
right now.
You can do the same and configure custom
agents where you can in the front matter.
Of that file create a tool set as well,
so you have them organised per agent as
well.
And on the fly again you can use the.
The tool set menu or yeah,
that that should work for you.
Perfect. Thanks.
And all right. So that's cool.
Thanks for that thought.
And uh, let's see so.
We're back to our our slides then.
So uh, understand the difference in ask.
So the next mode would be edit mode.
So I'm a.
Historical perspective that was this is
the next ability with the idea that we
can actually.
We'll go ahead and end the conversation.
Do we end up with a north file?
We have our test file here,
our large file.
But here what you can do is you can
actually um.
Bring up a chat window by hitting control
I or you can right-click on a selected
piece of code.
You can add the file to chat,
open the inline chat,
which is what I just did,
which brings up a dialogue where we can
actually say.
What we wanted to do,
we can add additional context,
we can say what model we want to use and
this is directly inside of a of an
existing file and whatever whatever we do
will be actually added to our our our
test file here.
Um.
Is.
So, so anyway, so that's it,
that's the inline chat version and that
allows us to to do code or we can expect
we can put a a chat down here and since
we're in edit mode and we have this file
open,
it will it will insert whatever we ask it
to generate into the.
The existing file that's open.
So this is basically this improvement
allows us to actually get a little closer
to a lot easier to generate content and
do input into files because we can
actually have it do the edits then was
added to.
The agent mode where we can actually now
delegate tasks.
To the to the agent and have it do things
for us so we can be much more broad about
what we want copilot to do and this is
where we bring in these tools or we can
execute the tools all in working in agent
mode.
One thing I should mention is that you
know ask mode and edit mode don't require
or don't consume any.
Don't consume any any premium tokens,
but agent mode every every request in
agent mode uses whatever the token.
Whatever the the token consumption rate
we'd actually be using.
So the idea would be if it could,
so it would consume 1 token,
even if you're only asking it a question,
it would still consume a a premium token.
And so you want to be somewhat if you're
if you're if you're worried about premium
token consumption is to make sure that
you're using ask ask mode and edit mode
when you when you when you can and and
avoid that consumption penalty.
From from using it.
So and and and try to try to you only use
agent mode when you actually actually
need to.
And I my solution to that problem is just
to get more premium tokens.
By upgrading my my subscription, but uh,
you may not have that option.
All right, questions here.
All right, well,
let's see what's next in our deck.
I think we're pretty close to where we
wanted to go. Yep.
So when we come back from from break,
I'm going to go over my programming
briefly.
There was an ask that you install a tool.
So if you weren't able to get that tool
installed,
if you could try to install it during the
break, that would be great.
If you have any questions on installing
it,
let me know and we'll try to get those
resolved before we come back and start in
with.
Uh, actually coding with compiler.
Great. I'll see you guys in an hour.
See you soon.
All right.
So just so we know we're going to close
this chat,
close this meeting and we'll start a new
meeting when we when we pick this up.
After the break.